all right
[Music]
there is a constellation of new choices
in the dairy case these days from
almonds to oats such that major Dairy
corporations are going out of business
but a set of recommendations on healthy
beverage Choice from like 12 to 24
months of age cautioned that these
plant-based milks are not adequate
nutritional substitutes for dairy milk
with the exception of fortified soy milk
the report and the Press coverage
immediately triggered an outcry from the
medical community for many reasons
including the concern around conflicts
of interest as several of these
endorsing organizations received funds
from the dairy industry the one such
organization is accused of trying to
cover that fact up by removing the
national Dairy Council from their list
of sponsors immediately after the report
was released
but what about the merits of the report
well after weaning milk of any kind is
not required and really shouldn't be
relied upon as a main source of calories
children will be fine with water and
healthy food if you are going to give
kids milk there would seem to be a
better choice although cow's milk is
rich in calcium it does not appear to
clearly reduce fractures and most
plant-based milks on the market have the
same amount more importantly the
consumption of cow's milk carries risks
including a potential association with
type 1 diabetes onset anemia in toddlers
lactose intolerance calcium protein
allergy and infantile colic I've got a
bunch of videos on those topics so the
adverse effects from just normal
consumption of cow's milk must be
compared against the risks from
plant-based milks which are problematic
mainly when used inappropriately meaning
like to the exclusion of most other
Foods diets that are clearly
inappropriate like the case of
kwashiorkor in Atlanta because this diet
was basically 99 percent rice milk
plant-based milks have the benefit of
being low in saturated fat free of
cholesterol and though the protein
content is generally lower than in cow's
milk plant-based smokes are said to be
richer in terms of fiber that's
technically true since cow's milk has
zero fiber but the fiber contents of
plant-based smokes are pretty pitiful
certainly compared to the Whole Foods
from which they were derived I mean a
couple soybeans themselves would have
more than 10 grams but still soy milk is
likely the least processed out of all
plant-based milks it's basically just
soak Crush cook and strain and is said
to be the only non-dairy milk that
contains the same amount of protein as
cow's milk that may have once been true
but now there's pea milk which is also
comparable protein-wise they all tend to
have the same calcium and vitamin D
levels and fewer calories as many as
five times fewer calories than cow's
milk in fact
soy milk has the additional benefit of
reducing breast cancer risk in girls and
normalizing development soy milk
consumption is also associated with
lower prostate cancer risk in men and
Interventional studies suggests improved
gut health by boosting the growth of
good bacteria soy milk has
anti-inflammatory effects lowering sea
react to protein levels has desirable
effects on phosphorus metabolism
compared to cow's milk significantly
reduces free radical DNA damage compared
to rice milk or cow's milk prevents bone
loss and post-menopausal women when put
to the test and can
improve insulin resistance soy milk can
help with stroke rehab improving walking
speed exercise endurance grip strength
and muscle functionality as well as
lower blood pressure in men and women
better than cow's milk not to mention
lowering your LDL cholesterol as much as
25 after just 21 days it is quite clear
that nutritionally soy milk is the best
alternative for replacing cow's milk in
the human diet
yes there are all sorts of benefits of
plant-based versus other based milks no
casein cholesterol lactose less
saturated fat actually has a bit of
fiber but what about the Specter of
anti-nutrients is there even such a
thing as anti-nutrients long-standing
evidence suggests that consuming a diet
rich in plant-based Foods plays a
significant role in prevention and
reduction of chronic diseases such as
cardiovascular disease cancer stroke
dementia diabetes cataracts and others
despite the need to increase plant food
consumption there have been some
concerns raised about whether they are
beneficial because of the various
so-called anti-nutrient compounds they
contain it's true there are some
compounds when eaten in high enough
quantities especially when taken in
isolation can have adverse effects whole
plant Foods also contain thousands of
other compounds in the food Matrix
though many which counteract the
potential effects of the anti-nutrients
plant-based diets are associated with a
reduced risk of Lifestyle induced
chronic diseases the thousands of
phytonutrients that contain promote
antioxidant defense for example reduce
inflammation in some cases what has been
referred to as anti-nutrients May in
fact be therapeutic agents for various
conditions see for example my video
series in the world phytates and the
prevention and treatment of cancer I
don't want to end without emphasizing
one of the plant-based Pros no lactose
people don't understand that the
majority of adults humans on planet
Earth are unable to digest cow's milk
throughout childhood the enzyme you have
that breaks down the milk sugar lactose
begins to decline in most individuals
throughout the world which makes sense
since milk is for babies
why would we need to digest it after
weaning from the breast and so most
people experience symptoms like bloating
abdominal pain intestinal gas and watery
stool or even nausea and vomiting the
global prevalence estimate of lactose
malabsorption is more than two out of
three people and the United States is
more like one out of three but 95 of
Asians 60 to 80 percent of African
Americans in Ashkenazi Jews 80 to 100
percent of American Indians and 50 to 80
percent of Hispanics have trouble
digesting milk
it's really mostly those of northern
European origin who can handle it
throughout adulthood so to say everyone
should drink milk seems like an example
of racial bias in federal nutrition
policy it's like they're assuming
everyone is of northern European descent
overall about 75 percent of the world's
population including 25 of those in the
United States lose their lactase enzymes
after weaning to fight the vitamin D
disease rickets they had to choose
something and the food supply to fortify
with vitamin D choosing Dairy is ironic
since individuals of African ancestry
because of their darker skin or it
particularly high risk for vitamin D
deficiency yet most can't properly
digest it
but there is some good news for reasons
like these Canada has recently removed
Dairy as a separate Food Group in their
National dietary guidance in 2019 the
new Canada's dietary guidelines and food
guide were released having undergone a
thorough review and update to emphasize
the importance of consuming more
plant-based products another major
change Was the removal of dairy as a
separate food group with wait for it
water included as the beverage of choice
what a concept the attenuated emphasis
on dairy products and the increased
focus on plant-based Foods in Canada
were based on several parameters
including the removal of industry-funded
studies from consideration as part of
the evidence base
[Music]
thank you